Records of the San Juan de la Cruz Hacienda (Mexico), 1649-1805
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Records of the San Juan de la Cruz Hacienda (Mexico), 1649-1805
MS 086
San Juan de la Cruz Hacienda (Mexico)
Sixteen manuscripts, dated between 1649 and 1805, consisting of legal proceedings, receipts, deeds, and business records relating to the San Juan de la Cruz Hacienda and flour mill, which was located in Nueva Vizcaya, New Spain (in the present state of Chihuahua, Mexico).
0.1 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
The original name, as it appears in the documents, was Hacienda de San Nicolás or, alternatively, Rancho de San Nicolás, derived from the Chapel of San Nicolás which was built at the Hacienda of Juan Muñoz Olvera, in the later seventeenth century. It was located in the San Bartolomé Valley, Nueva Vizcaya, New Spain (present day state of Chihuahua, Mexico).
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Series I: Documents 1649-1805
Scope and Content Note
Sixteen manuscripts, dated 1649-1805, that contain legal proceedings, receipts, deeds and business records relating to the hacienda and flour mill, located in the jurisdiction of the Valle de San Bartolomé, Nueva Vizcaya, New Spain (present day state of Chihuahua, Mexico. The original 1666 building permit for the chapel is present; issued by the Bishop of Durango, and it was renewed from 1678 to 1775. Other late seventeenth century items include receipts and statements of debt relating to Captain Juan Gutiérrez, Juana Gutiérrez, and Second Lieutenant Juan Ponce de León. Among the eighteenth century records are a levy for pious work, title costs for a cattle and horse pasture, an inventory, and sale records for the hacienda with Don Augustín de Soto named as the owner.
Access Terms
Olvera, Juan Muñoz de
Gutiérrez, Juan
Gutiérrez Haces, Juana
Gutiérrez Haces, Juana
León, Juan Ponce de—18th century
Soto, Augustín de
Haciendas—Mexico—Chihuahua (State)—History—Sources
Flour mills—Mexico—Chihuahua (State)—History—Sources
San Juan de la Cruz Hacienda (Mexico)—History—Sources
Chihuahua (Mexico: State)—History—Sources
Nueva Vizcaya (New Spain)—History—Sources
Mexico—History—Spanish colony, 1540-1810
San Bartolomé Valley (Mexico)
Container List
- Series I: Documents 1649-1805
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Legal proceedings undertaken by the alcalde mayor of the Pueblo y Valle de San Bartolomé. 1649 (date of seal), 1676 (date of document), 1649, 1676 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, Statements of Debts, Notes, etc. mostly relating to Capt. Juan Gutierrez, his wife Juana Gutierrez, and the Alferez Juan Ponce de Leon of the Rancho of San Nicolás. 7 pp., 1664-1688 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fragment. Legal proceedings? Valle de San Bartolomé. Damaged. 1 pp., 1676 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - License or permit to construct a chapel on the Hacienda (and Flour Mill) of Juan Muñoz de Olvera located in the jurisdiction of the Valle de San Bartolomé. Chapel to be called San Nicolás. Permit issued by the Bishop of Durango. Kingdom of Nueva Vizcaya. Verso of p. 1 and pp. 2-6 are renewals of the above permit., 1666, 1678-1775 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Statement of funds., 1687 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Papers relating to the sale of the Rancho and Mill of San Nicolás, 1778. Includes copy of earlier deed, 1698. 5 pp., 1698, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Papers relating to the ownership of the Hacienda of San Nicolás. 18 pp., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Levy for “pious work.” Valle de San Bartolomé. March 26, 1732. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - (9) Fragment of a deed? 1733? 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Summary of costs involved in issuing title to a pasture for cattle and horses (ganado mayor). Damaged. March 1759. Valle de San Bartolomé. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inventory and papers relating to the sale of the Hacienda de San Nicolás to the sole bidder at public auction, Don Augustín Soto. Certified in Durango, Sept. 19, 1774. 19 pp. Damaged. Incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Assorted documents dated 1728-1800 relating to the affairs of the Hacienda de San Nicolás. Autos (decrees), ecclesiastical papers, etc. 17 pp. (Bound with #11) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed to the Hacienda de San Nicolas and its flour mill disposed of through public sale. Augustín de Soto. June 27, 1778. 12 pp. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Receipt for 506 pesos (fees of this parish). Augustín Soto. Parral. March 13, 1800. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Receipt for 506 pesos (fees of this parish). Augustín Soto. Parral. March 13, 1800. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Document of the Hacienda of San Nicolás. June 15, 1805. 1 p. Damaged. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fragment. 1 p., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)